<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Harmonic Algebra Trainer</string>
    <string name="helpIntro">        <![CDATA[
        <h2>Introduction</h2>
        This app is a tool designed to help learning the circle of fifths and the relations which the circle represents. Also, later releases
        contain ear training modes.

<br><br>
        Namely:

  <ul>
    <li> Cycle of fifths - function quiz</li>
    <li> Cycle of fifths -  Signature quiz</li>
    <li> Ear trainer </li>
    <li> Progression trainer </li>
  </ul>

<h2>Bug reporting, feedback, etc.</h2>
Let me kindly ask you to:
<ul>
<li> Report bugs if you encounter any. You can do so on github ( http://github.com/kareltucek/HarmonigAlgebraQuiz ).</li>
<li> Leave some feedback. If you do not want to post publicly or to give bad ratings, you are welcome to drop me a few words to my tucek.karel mailbox hosted at gmail. </li>
<ul>


    <h2>Credits</h2>
    This app was written by Karel TuÄek. As with all my publicly available
    projects, it was written with my own needs in mind - i.e., it was designed to be simple and useful, not to generate
    profit. Not necessarily nice & intuitive, but with configuration options uncensored for the sake of simplicity.
  ]]>
    </string>

    <string name="helpEar">        <![CDATA[
        <h2>Introduction</h2>
        The ear trainer provides a tool for improving relative musical hearing via Alain Benbassat\'s method, also often abbreviated
        as "FET - Functional Ear Trainer". This method is
        already available on desktop via https://www.miles.be/ flash app and on android via "Functional Ear Trainer". This
        implementation provides less user comfort :-), yet is designed on a slightly different philosophy, fixing some drawbacks
        of the other implementations.

        <h2>The aims</h2>

        At the end of training, the user should be able to confidently recognize degrees of a scale by ear. The learning process
        is designed to build up the ability by small steps without any prerequisites.

        <h2>The method</h2>

          The basic idea of the method is that tones should be always recognized within context of a key. Within the key,
          every degree is to be associated with a specific sensation ("colour/taste of the sound"). The key is established via
          playing a cadence - chord progression of tonic, subdominant and dominant, which substitutes intro of a music piece.

<br><br>
          Every training question consists of the following three steps:
          <ul>
          <li> First, the key is established by playing a cadence (this may happen at the begenning of a quiz or at the beginning of every question).   </li>
          <li> Then, a tone is played and the user is asked to guess the tone as a degree of the reference key.</li>
          <li> Finally the trainer plays resolution towards the nearest tonic.</li>
          </ul>

          The learning process goes as follows in multiple phases. Each phase may take weeks or even months of daily training. Each phase
          should end by the user reaching a steady 98%+ score.

          <ul>
            <li> In the first phase the user associates a tone stimuli with the resolution pattern and some sensation. This creates
             a new brain connection for each harmonic function of the basic Major scale.</li>
            <li> In further phases, restrictions (like single-octave mode, cadences/resolutions) are dropped,
                and the user\'s neural network is relearned so that it unlearns
                undesired connections which were established in the first phase. First, dependence on octave should be eliminated, later
                fixation on tonic and dependence on cadences and resolutions. </li>
            <li> After mastering the Major context, the user should continue by learning chromatic tones in major context.
               This is vital to eliminate pattern dependence. Otherwise, the brain will
               mix up similar tone sequences in different scale types.
                </li>
            <li> After mastering the major context, the user should continue with minor context.</li>
          </ul>

          At the end of the process, the user should be able to hear melodies in contexts of their keys. For instance, to write
          down music without using the trial-and-error approach.

        <h2>Implementation Differences</h2>

          <ul>
          <li> Our ear trainer is a learning tool, not a game. We allow selective replay of cadences when necessary. Also,
          we do not penalize "giveups" by lowering score, since making correct associations is much more important
          for the learning process than getting a good score via "wild guesses".</li>
          <li> We take into account the interference caused by previous question in cadence-less mode. For this reason, we
          end resolutions by playing the last question tone again after resolution ends. This way, the user is able to
          learn to keep old reference frame without being affected by the "tonic-to-question" relation.</li>
          <li> We implement "tricky questions", which intentionally repeats incorrectly inputted pairs, allowing for conscious learning
          and fixing problems.</li>
          </ul>

        <h2>Tips</h2>
          <ul>
          <li>Always aim for score of 99%.</li>
          <li>Giving up does not lower your score. If you are not sure, better give up and try to create/fix the missing association.</li>
          <li>You can replay cadence, last question and current question at will. Use this ability.</li>
          <li>By default, incorrect or gave-up questions are repeated again after a while within the same question set. Use this
              knowledge to fix problems.</li>
          <li>Think about the learning process. Think about which associations you are creating. If something does not work, try to
              figure out why, and fix it.</li>
          <li>Experiment with different modes and settings. Specific settings will help you overcome specific problems encountered
              during the learning process.</li>
          <li>Variation in the learning process may speed up learning. </li>
          <li>Mastering the major context with resolutions is not sufficient to apply the learned abilities in practice.
              You need to continue with the chromatic mode. You need to learn to keep context of the current key (despite
              out-of-scale tones) or to switch to new key at will.</li>
          <li>After mastering the chromatic mode, you should continue by training with this app and your instrument. The question
              type contains "continue" modes which will play question by question without any interaction.</li>
          <li>Think about interferences. Typically, in resolution or cadence mode, the brain will associate tones with respect to the last tone
              of resolution (tonic) or the last chord of cadence (again tonic), yet in practice the last played tone is not tonic. For this
              purpose, we provide question modes which repeat the previous question after playing its cadence/resolution. This allows the
              brain to learn to keep the key context with respect to the last question degree & interval.</li>
          <li>Be warned. The new brain algebra will interfere with your old one. Using this app may temporarily yet significantly reduce
              your regular musical abilities and vice versa. You will have to learn how to connect the two into one.</li>
          </ul>


  ]]>
    </string>

    <string name="helpKey">        <![CDATA[


  <h2>Harmonic function quiz</h2>
  Harmonic function quiz determines the key by specifying either major tonic or minor tonic. Determining
  the rest of harmonic functions is up to the user. When all degrees were encountered twice, new key is selected.
   The following notation is used:

  <ul>
  <li> D for dominant</li>
  <li> S for subdominant</li>
  <li> T for tonic</li>
  <li> Uppercase letters mark major chords, lowercase mark minor chords.</li>
  <li> dim for the last chord of the scale not covered by the D,S,T,d,s,t letters</li>
  </ul>

  For instance, lets assume that the first line reads "T = C", it means that we are in C major scale (i.e., C is the tonic). Dominant
  chord is then G (because it lays one step to the right on the fifths cycle), so if the question reads "D" (as Dominant), the correct
  answer is "G". If the question reads S as Subdominant, the answer is "F", because F is one step to the left on the cycle.

<br><br>
  If the letter is lowercase, parallel minor chord has to be entered. E.g., minor tonic of C major is "a".

<br><br>
  We try to sum up motivation for this function quiz in the following section, however, we strongly encourage the reader to study
  the music theory from more elaborate resources. The reader should understand:

  <ul>
    <li> Construction of scales</li>
    <li> Diatonic chord system</li>
    <li> German function theory (covered e.g. by wikipedia "Function (music)" article).</li>
    <li> Viennese function theory</li>
  </ul>

  <h2>Signature quiz</h2>
  In the signature quiz, the user is given a number of flats or sharps and is supposed to determine the
  scale. First, all major scales are iterated in one block, followed by another minor block.

  <h2>Importance of fifths</h2>
  Simply stated, our ear likes consonance of tones whose frequency is given by a simple fraction. In other words,
  those which yield short period even when added together.
<br><br>
  The simplest consonance is given by 2:1 fraction. Which does not count because it is the same tone, just sounding "an octave higher".
<br><br>
  The next simplest fraction is 3:2, which gives exactly the "fifth". I.e., the fifth tone in a common scale (or the 7th tone in the 12 tone system).
<br><br>
  The next simplest fraction is 4:3, which gives the fourth. The fourth is basically an inverted fifth, because the distance from a fifth tone
  of a scale to the next tonic" is the fourth. Also, note that the two fractions "added" together (3/2*4/3) yield exactly the next tonic one octave higher.
<br><br>
  The other intervals are more complicated, but the concept of inversion applies too - (minor) sixth is an inverted (major) third,
  (major) sixth is an inverted (minor) third and so on.
<br><br>
  Since the distance of a fifth is given by a simple fraction, the consonance of such two tones is good. We may also say that "being in the distance of a fifth"
  is a good metric of musical relatedness of tones.
  Regarding other intervals, major thirds and minor thirds work well in both melodic successions and in harmonic context (i.e., played at the same time).
  Seconds work in melodic successions, but not in harmonic context. Augmented fourth degrees are sometimes used in songs,
  but generally (as intervals of two consecutive tones), augmented fourths and diminished fifths work in neither melodic succession nor in harmonic context.
  There are exceptions to *all* these rules, but these rules are a reasonable approximation to begin with.

  <h2> Equivalency of Minor and Major scales </h2>
  Western music is founded on a 12 tone system. These 12 tones are evenly spread so that if we take a tone and multiply its frequency by 2^(1/12),
   we get the next tone in the sequence. (Such tuning is called "evenly temperated". There are other tuning systems, which are however out of
    scope of this text.)
<br><br>
    Furthermore, 7 tones out of these 12 are selected to form a scale. Which seven tones should be selected is not strictly given, but
    practical concerns yield one popular pattern, which has distances 2-2-1-2-2-2-1 (or any rotation of these). Some of the reasons for
    popularity of this pattern follow:

  <ul>
  <li> Tones in this pattern form one consistent sequence of Fifths. I.e., if we take an arbitrary tone and then seventimes take next tone
   as the fifth of the previous one, we get this pattern.</li>
  <li> If we take an arbitrary tone in this pattern and count the fifth or fourth tone from it, we get the perfect fifth or fourth. Except
   for one position which yields augmented fourth/diminished fifth. That's one of the reasons why these intervals
    are called perfect - they are (almost) always the same ones.</li>
    <li> Only two of the seven tones have a distance of augmented fourth (/diminished fifth) to some other tone (namely to each other). If we remove these two, we get so called pentatonic scale, in which no minor second or augmented fourth is found.</li>
    <li> More than 7 tones don't work well, because 8th fifth (or any other tone) would yield another augmented fourth (/dim. fifth), which would furthermore be found in a one-step distance between two other tones.
        While such tones may be used in more exotic melodic successions (jazz, bues, etc.), they are impractical for standard "simple" harmony,
        because we need to choose just one of them anyway.</li>
  </ul>

  If we take the discussed pattern, we get major scale. If we take the same pattern, but begin at its sixth position, we get a minor scale - a
  scale on exactly same tones as the major scale.

  <h2>Creating new scales</h2>
  Furthermore, if we take an existing major scale, we can create a new one by taking its fifth degree as a tonic, and applying a sharp on its third position.
  Alternatively, we can do the inverse - starting at the fourth degree and adding a flat to the seventh degree.

    <h2>The Circle of Fifths</h2>
    The circle of fifths visualises the described relations of adding flats or sharps, as well as the relation of "being a fifth to" or "being a
    fourth to", and also the relation of "taking 7 related scale-forming tones". The circle (or a mental picture of the circle) can be
     used to quickly determind all those relations if memorized.
<br><br>
    It is a simple circle consisting of all the 12 tones, arranged so that the neighbouring tones are in the distance of fifths
    and fourths. Namely for every node, the node to the right is in the distance of a fifth. The node to the left is in the distance of a fourth
    (which is the distance of a fifth from the perspective of that node).
<br><br>
    Furthermore, we can inscribe another circle if fifths into the first one, shifted by 3 positions. This way, we get the dual minor-major roles aligned,
    as well as both tonic-subdominant-dominant algebras.


    <h2>Chords and Harmonic Algebras</h2>

    The idea is that each degree of a scale (a note or a chord based on the note)
    represents a unique harmonic function. If we take a regular major/minor scale and build
    a chord on each degree of the scale, we will get three major chords, three minor chords and one diminished
    chord. Furthermore, we can take these triplets and construct simple harmonic algebras of them, each
    consisting of a tonic (chord based on first degree), subdominant (chord based on fourth degree) and dominant (chord based on fifth degree).
    (One of the triplets is based on major tonic while the other triplet is based on the minor tonic of the scale in question.)
<br><br>
    Within a major scale we get:

  <ul>
    <li> 1th degree - major tonic</li>
    <li> 2nd degree - minor subdominant</li>
    <li> 3th degree - minor dominant</li>
    <li> 4th degree - major subdominant</li>
    <li> 5th degree - major dominant</li>
    <li> 6th degree - minor tonic</li>
    <li> 7th degree - diminished singleton</li>
    </ul>

    Within a minor scale, we ge exactly the same, except the numbers will be shifted by -2 (or +5) degrees.
<br><br>
    Each triplet consists of a tonic, subdominant and a dominant. These are all in row on the circle of fifths, since dominant stand for fifth degree and
    subdominant stands for fourth degree(, which is just an inverted fifth). I.e., if we look at the circle, each three consecutive chords
    form one subdominant-tonic-dominant algebra.
<br><br>
    In music, these degrees have distinct functions:
  <ul>
    <li> Tonic is the basic chord - the home chord. It evokes sensation of relaxation, satisfaction. Songs are usually
    started with this chord and always finished with it.</li>
    <li> Dominant is a chord found usually at the end of a verse, before tonic.
    It evokes the sensation of unrest, dissatisfaction, a sort of a desire to return back to tonic.
    It shares its first degree with the tonic.</li>
    <li> Subdominant sounds a bit as the dominant. Just different. In music, it is usually found somewhere around other chords. It is the detour
    on song's way from tonic to dominant. It shares its last degree with the tonic.</li>
    </ul>

    The simplest major-scale songs can be accompanied by a (major) tonic and a (major) dominant only, rarely encountering the
    major subdominant too.
<br><br>
    Pieces in minor scales (and more complex major ones too) are more complicated. They combine both major
    and minor algebras and sometimes throw in the diminished degree or some out-of-scale tones too (E.g.,
    forming a major chord in place of a minor one). Tonic-subdominant-dominant algebras may not always
    be the best choice (or the sufficient choice) for understanding harmony of such pieces, for instance because simple
    simple degree-by-degree chord successions are used.



  ]]>

    </string>
</resources>
