<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Harmonic Algebra Quiz</string>
    <string name="help">        <![CDATA[
    <h2>Introduction</h2>
        This app is a tool designed to help learning the circle of fifths and the relations which the circle represents.

        For this purpose, there are two types of quizes:

  <ul>
  <li> Harmonic function quiz</li>
  <li> Signature quiz</li>
  </ul>

        Furthermore, we try to explain some related chapters of the music theory in the following text.

<h2>Bug reporting, feedback, etc.</h2>
But first, let me kindly ask you to:
<ul>
<li>Report bugs if you encounter any. You can do so on github ( http://github.com/kareltucek/HarmonigAlgebraQuiz ).</li>
<li>Leave some feedback. If you do not want to post publicly or to give bad ratings, you are welcome to drop me a few words to my tucek.karel mailbox hosted at gmail. </li>
<ul>

  <h2>Harmonic function quiz</h2>
  Harmonic function quiz determines the key by specifying either major tonic or minor tonic. Determining
  the rest of harmonic functions is up to the user. When all degrees were encountered twice, new key is selected.
   The following notation is used:

  <ul>
  <li> D for dominant</li>
  <li> S for subdominant</li>
  <li> T for tonic</li>
  <li> Uppercase letters mark major chords, lowercase mark minor chords.</li>
  </ul>

  <h2>Signature quiz</h2>
  In the signature quiz, the user is given a number of flats or sharps and is supposed to determine the
  scale. First, all major scales are iterated in one block, followed by another minor block.

  <h2>Importance of fifths</h2>
  Simply stated, our ear likes consonance of tones whose frequency is given by a simple fraction. In other words,
  those which yield short period even when added together.
<br><br>
  The simplest consonancy is given by 2:1 fraction. Which does not count because it is the same tone, just sounding a "bit higher".
<br><br>
  The next simplest fraction is 3:2, which gives exactly the "fifth". I.e., the fifth tone in a common scale (or the 7th tone in the 12 tone system).
<br><br>
  The next simplest fraction is 4:3, which gives the fourth. The fourth is basically an inverted fifth, because the distance from a fifth tone
  of a scale to the next tonic" is the fourth. Also, note that the two fractions "added" together (3/2*4/3) yield exactly the next tonic one octave higher.
<br><br>
  The other intervals are more complicated, but the concept of inversion applies too - (minor) sixth is an inverted (major) third,
  (major) sixth is an inverted (minor) third and so on.
<br><br>
  So the relation of "being in the distance of a fifth" of two ones is important because their consonancy is the "best one".
  Furthermore, major thirds and minor thirds work well in both melodic successions and in harmonic context (i.e., played at the same time).
  Seconds work in melodic successions, but not in harmonic context. Augmented fourths/diminished fifths work in neither melodic succession nor in harmonic context.
  There are exceptions to *all* these rules, but this is a reasonable rule of thumb.

  <h2> Equivalency of Minor and Major scales </h2>
  Western music is founded on a 12 tone system. These 12 tones are evenly spread so that if we take a tone and multiply its frequency by 2^(1/12),
   we get the next tone in the sequence.
<br><br>
    Furthermore, 7 tones out of these 12 are selected to form a scale. Which seven tones should be selected is not strictly given, but
    practical concerns yield one popular pattern, which has distances 2-2-1-2-2-2-1 (or any rotation of these). Some of the reasons for
    popularity of this pattern follow:

  <ul>
  <li>Tones in this pattern form one consistent sequence of Fifths. I.e., if I take an arbitrary tone and then seventimes take next tone
   as the fifth of the previous one, I get this pattern.</li>
  <li>If I take an arbitrary tone in this pattern and count the fifth or fourth tone from it, I always get the perfect fifth or fourth. Ehm, except
   for one position, but that cannot be fixed. But except this one, I never get an augmented fourth or diminished fifth. That's why these intervals
    are called perfect - they are (almost) always the same ones.</li>
    <li>Only two of the seven tones have a distance of augmented fourth (/diminished fifth) to some other tone. If we remove these two, we get so called pentatonic scale.</li>
    <li>More than 7 tones don't work, because 8th fifth (or any other tone) would have distance of augmented fourth (/diminished fifth) to more than two other tones.</li>
  </ul>

  If we take the discussed pattern, we get major scale. If we take the same pattern, but begin at its sixth position, we get a minor scale - a
  scale on exactly same tones as the major scale.

  <h2>Creating new scales</h2>
  Furthermore, if we take an existing major scale, we can create a new one by taking its fifth degree as a tonic, and applying a sharp on its third position.
  Alternatively, we can do the inverse - starting at the fourth degree and adding a flat to the seventh degree.

    <h2>The Circle of Fifths</h2>
    The circle of fifths visualises the described relations of adding flats or sharps, as well as the relation of "being a fifth to" or "being a
    fourth to", and also the relation of "taking 7 related scale-forming tones". The circle (or a mental picture of the circle) can be
     used to quickly determind all those relations if memorized.
<br><br>
    It is a simple circle consisting of all the 12 tones, arranged so that the neighbouring tones are in the distance of fifths
    and fourths. Namely for every node, the node to the right is in the distance of a fifth. The node to the left is in the distance of a fourth
    (which is the distance of a fifth from the perspective of that node).
<br><br>
    Furthermore, we can inscribe another circle if fifths into the first one, shifted by 3 positions. This way, we get the dual minor-major roles aligned,
    as well as both tonic-subdominant-dominant algebras.


    <h2>Chords and Harmonic Algebras</h2>

    The idea is that each degree of a scale (a note or a chord based on the note)
    represents a unique harmonic function. If we take a regular major/minor scale and build
    a chord on each degree of the scale, we will get three major chords, three minor chords and one diminished
    chord. Furthermore, we can take these triplets and construct simple harmonic algebras of them, each
    consisting of a tonic (chord based on first degree), subdominant (chord based on fourth degree) and dominant (chord based on fifth degree).
    (One of the triplets is based on major tonic while the other triplet is based on the minor tonic of the scale in question.)
<br><br>
    Within a major scale we get:

  <ul>
    <li> 1th degree - major tonic</li>
    <li> 2nd degree - minor subdominant</li>
    <li> 3th degree - minor dominant</li>
    <li> 4th degree - major subdominant</li>
    <li> 5th degree - major dominant</li>
    <li> 6th degree - minor tonic</li>
    <li> 7th degree - diminished singleton</li>
    </ul>

    Within a minor scale, we ge exactly the same, except the numbers will be shifted by -2 (or +5) degrees.
<br><br>
    Each triplet consists of a tonic, subdominant and a dominant. These are all in row on the circle of fifths, since dominant stand for fifth degree and
    subdominant stands for fourth degree(, which is just an inverted fifth). I.e., if we look at the circle, each three consecutive chords
    form one subdominant-tonic-dominant algebra.
<br><br>
    In music, these degrees have distinct functions:
  <ul>
    <li>Tonic is the basic chord - the home chord. It evokes sensation of relaxation, satisfaction. Songs are usually
    started with this chord and always finished with it.</li>
    <li>Dominant is a chord found usually at the end of a verse, before tonic.
    It evokes the sensation of unrest, dissatisfaction, a sort of a desire to return back to tonic.
    It shares its first degree with the tonic.</li>
    <li>Subdominant sounds a bit as the dominant. Just different. In music, it is usually found somewhere around other chords. It is the detour
    on song's way from tonic to dominant. It shares its last degree with the tonic.</li>
    </ul>

    The simplest major-scale songs can be accompanied by a (major) tonic and a (major) dominant only, rarely encountering the
    major subdominant too.
<br><br>
    Pieces in minor scales (and more complex major ones too) are more complicated. They combine both major
    and minor algebras and sometimes throw in the diminished degree or some out-of-scale tones too (E.g.,
    forming a major chord in place of a minor one). Tonic-subdominant-dominant algebras may not always
    be the best choice (or the sufficient choice) for understanding harmony of such pieces, for instance because simple
    simple degree-by-degree chord successions are used.

    <h2>Credits</h2>
    This app is brought to you by Karel TuÄek, as open-source (no ads, free of charge, under MIT licence). As with all my publicly available
    projects, it was written with my own needs in mind - i.e., it was designed to be simple and useful, not to generate
    profit.


  ]]>

    </string>
</resources>
